[Music]
in my last video I noted how lying at a
slight six degre head down tilt for a
few hours can boost fat burning now
obviously you wouldn't want to lie
tilted back if you had a heart condition
such as congestive heart failure as many
as 8 to 12 cups of blood may be
displaced into the Torso from the
extremities at a tilt like that so you
you have to have the cardiovascular
fitness to handle it acid reflux could
also be a problem in fact we typically
tell heartburn patients to do the
reverse put a few bricks under the post
at the head of their bed to have gravity
work in their favor to keep stomach acid
down where it belongs but for those
without medical problems is there a harm
to lying tilted back for a few hours
well it could give you a space headache
in movies after astronauts are shown
practicing underwater but the gold
standard for simulating the
physiological effects of the
weightlessness of outer space is
hdbr head down bed rest on Earth our
blood tends to collect in our legs so
our body is designed to force blood
headward in outer space our body is
still trying to push our blood up so
without Earth's gravity blood pushes
upwards to our head and chest just like
it does when we lie till tilted back
this realization came from cosmonauts
returning from the space station feeling
as though they were slipping towards the
foot of the bed and only feeling quote
unquote normal when they were tilted 6°
back all the extra blood pooling in the
head is thought to contribute to the
headaches reported by up to 70% of
astronauts during space flights and a
similar percentage of individuals suffer
headaches from prolonged head down bed
rest um that's after days though in
preparation for a mission to Mars space
agencies put people through head down
bed rest for prolonged periods eating
bathing and toiling all while lying in
bed tilted back for literally months at
a time extended stretches of head down
positioning for weeks May impair lung
function brain function and immune
function and cause a loss of muscle mass
on the last Apollo Mission the
astronauts lost about 5 pounds of fat
over the 12-day trip but they also lost
about 2 lounds of lean body mass
prolonged weightlessness or bed rest
regardless of tilt can result in muscle
and bone loss but just sleeping on a
slant by putting a few bricks under the
post at the foot of your bed could
potentially give you a boost in fat
metabolism without the long-term adverse
effects if you want to try it a note of
caution take it slow when standing back
up after Just 4 hours of a 6° head down
tilt most people experience reduced
orthostatic tolerance when anyone stands
suddenly after sitting or lying down for
a while you can get a head rush you know
feel dizzy faint or laded as the blood
drains from your brain down into your
legs before your body can compensate
this can be exacerbated by lying with
your head tilted back so be careful get
up gradually drinking two cups of cold
water 30 minutes before Rising may also
help do not try this at home if you have
any heart or lung issues or problems
with your brain like head trauma or eyes
even a family history of glaucoma
disqualifies you ask your physician if
they think it's safe for you to sleep in
quote unquote mild trendelenberg
Friedrich trendelenberg was a pioneering
surgeon that popularized the use of what
was formerly referred to as head down
position for certain abdominal and
pelvic procedures angling the operating
table back 15 to 30° pull some abdominal
organs out of the way to help declutter
the surgical field resulting in what is
now widely known as the trendelenberg
position steep Trend delberg like 25 30°
tilt has been associated with transient
visual problems thought due to the
increase in pressure within the eyeball
cautions have been issued for those at
risk for glaucoma a disease of increased
eye pressure to avoid inversion therapy
where people hang upside down as well as
yoga positions like handstands which can
have a similar effect line L back in
mild trendelenberg like around 6° can
cause a fleeting bump in eye pressure
that appears to normalize within a few
hours but the pulling of blood in the
head May reduce blood flow to the retina
sufficient to impair nerve impulses uh
similar effects have been noted within
the brain intracranial pressure also
normalizes after a few hours at a six
degree head down tilt but the overall
blood flow through the brain does drop a
bit this is why you shouldn't try this
if you have eye or brain pathology
to my surprise sleeping in mild
trendelenberg was actually put to the
test to prevent bone loss in sedentary
individuals restrict people's activity
to walking less than 2 miles a day on
average and within a year they can lose
as much as 15% of their bone mineral
density what happened to those
randomized to the same exercise
restriction but also combined with
sleeping at a 2 degre head down tilt
that was increased by 2° about every 2
months so they ended up sleeping at a
14° sland or whatever angle they felt
comfortable with by the end of the year
not only did it completely block the
bone loss they built more bone despite
the movement restriction they ended up
with about 12% greater bone mineral
density than when they started note that
this bone building effect was only
apparent in sedentary individuals
another group randomized to the same
Mile and delburg but assigned to run an
average of 5 or six mil a day just
maintain their same skeletal Integrity
the study was repeated and the same
remarkable effects were found there's
something about the periodic fluid
redistribution that comes with sleeping
tilted back at night that actively
builds both bone density and volume
after the dayong stagnant pooling of
blood in the legs of sedentary
individuals the research team claims
that this is just the beginning to the
benefits citing quote unquote
unpublished studies asserting a near
Panacea of perk to sleeping in
Trendelenburg I can't be too critical of
this apparent Dodge when I can't point
to a single study supporting my
supposition that it'll help with weight
loss as far as I can tell it's never
been tried or even proposed what I can
promise is that any researchers who take
on the mantle of putting it to the test
will definitely have their study
featured in a video on
nutritionfacts.org
for